Guide to the Herbert F. Janick Jr. Papers MS 012
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
- Series 3: Subject Files, 38885
  - Oral Histories - Student Work - Introduction to Historical Research, 38894
    - Western Connecticut State University -- History., 38895
      - Ed Rosenberg (interview) Creator: Rosenberg, Ed Interviewer(s): Robert Barnes Interview location: unknown Running time: 50 min., May 6, 1998; 38916; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 11, Item 57)
        Coverage: 1956-1998
        Topics discussed: (side A): Background; hired in 1956 as part of the History/Social Science department; taught American history and Western Civilization; taught economics; gradually picked up more math courses; Math department; only Chester Floyd was there in beginning; as college grew, more math courses were needed; came point where he had to decide which department to teach and choose the math department and stayed until he retired in 1989; Physical changes between 1958; 1989; when he began, college was just Old Main, Fairfield Hall, and the original section of Higgins Hall; Berkshire was here and the gym had just been finished when he arrived; White Hall was still the high school in beginning; "the Hut" was here (Quonset Hut) that housed bookstore and lounge; Dr. Haas; very knowledgeable woman; school was her life; she did change over the years and adapted w/ the times; she was short changed by state w/ other universities due to her gender; Population; grew over the years; "Project Acorn"; the green between Berkshire and Higgins and Library and White was part of the beautification process; that area, the Quad, was originally a parking area; Parking; parking has always been a problem; had to take a ticket in order to get into parking lot, which saw several difficulties over years; Pre; Union history; faculty association in beginning, which was somewhat informal; this association had no power; could only have representation; usually held parties and other gatherings; in the 1970s, efforts made to form unions; Formation of Unions; AFT and AAUP, both teacher's unions; voted to go w/ the AAUP; Memorable moments; Vietnam War Era was a tense time; he had children in college at the time; they were hippies (one was arrested for demonstrating); Kent State; after incident, students at Western did a few things; once during faculty senate a group of students came asking for the campus to be closed down in observation of what happened at Kent State; a decision wasn't made immediately, but w/in a couple of days a group of students showed up at Dr. Haas' office demanding campus closing; Majors occurrences during 1960s; a microphone was set up on 7th Avenue where students would speak; while students sometimes demanding classes canceled, they never were; he did use time in his class to talk about the JFK assassination; Changes in students; attitude in how they took education; small percent went from high school to college in beginning; college went from privilege to a right; growth of college contributed to change; Spring events; "Sing Night" and "Skit Night" done by the four classes; brought everyone together and attended by everyone; gradually as college grew, this event disappeared; Older students; many were much more serious about their education than younger ones; tended to be better students and use time more efficiently; Student preparation; it began to fall off w/ increase of student population; the establishment of the Basic Studies program to keep numbers up; Basic Studies; brought in students who weren't college ready to prepare them; given special courses to give them experience; professors w/ Ph. D found teaching in program to be step down because it dealt w/ lower level material; Satisfaction w/ teaching career; he got involved w/ many things when he got to Western (started soccer); has kept in touch w/ many of his former students (particularly first ones); took a two; year leave between 1976; 78; took him awhile to get back involved in committees and such; didn't feel he had as much influence or contact w/ students; towards end it became less fun; Presidents; Dr. Haas was great supporter of students and had an open door policy; Dr. Bersi was very good and able to get more from the state; Dr. Feldman he wasn't a fan of and felt he shouldn't have been president; Dr. Roach he feels is a good person, but he never worked for him, so isn't sure of his work (does believe he is probably doing a good joB): Dr. Haas supporting her faculty; always protected them; once a member accused of being a communist (he wasn't) and she defended him; Dr. Bersi; did support faculty; wasn't on campus very much (side B): History of WestConn; one written by Dr. Charlotte Isham (1903; 1978); he wrote a follow; up later on; Expansion of college; been able to serve more students; take larger role in community; has separated the school however; Influence of WestConn; many of the recent mayors of Danbury have been WestConn grads; many principals and teachers in area are grads; has a good record and glad he worked at WestConn
      - Ed Rosenberg (interview) Creator: Rosenberg, Ed Interviewer(s): Donald Stissle and Andrew SanAngelo Interview location: El Gross Library in White Hall Running time: 70 min., Apr 29, 1996; 38915; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 11, Item 58)
        Coverage: 1956-1996
        Topics discussed: (side A): Background; went through the ethical cultural school system in NYC; started at MIT before going into WW II; got trained in meteorology and stationed in various places; graduated MIT in 1947; went to work in business in NYC (medical supplies), but didn't like it; went to Columbia Teacher's College; got Master's in History/Social Science education; taught in Chappaqua public school system from 1955; 56 (high school); left and came to Danbury State Teacher's College; DSTC; began teaching history/social sciences; taught a few math courses along the way; eventually told could only teach in one department and choose math; Teaching profession; wanted to go into it as a way to repay teachers for what they did for him; didn't make same money might have in business, but doesn't regret move; Working in two different departments; Dr. Burton Cook and him always got along; school grew from just elementary education to liberal arts; there weren't departments in beginning; wasn't until expansion they came; at one time all the sciences were together w/ math and the one teacher who taught it (Chester Floyd); eventually math department grew rapidly; Graduate programs; only taught a couple courses; usually taught lower level because he didn't have a math degree; it grew after they had secondary math majors; Early years; most enjoyable time; small school then and better opportunity to know more people; more in common w/ students because closer in age; began soccer team his second year here; Attitude change in students; in the 1950s, it was an institution where the students went along w/ what the administration said w/ little resistance; many in students in the 1950s were first generation college students; gradually more older students (married mothers) came in and very serious and good students; as the school grew in the 1960s, more students came in and started questioning things; Faculty meetings; gradually grew bigger w/ expansion of college; David Driscoll, professor in humanities, was old fashioned and when he spoke everybody paid attention; meetings eventually turned into the faculty senate; Faculty Senate; as the Vietnam War proceeded, many faculty became opposed to it; students began asking for more voice in things and wanted to be on committees at the school; faculty was shocked at first, but some felt it would be beneficial; Kent State; demonstrations began after the incident; several people talked, including himself; students wanted Dr. Haas to close school after that and went to her office; he told group she didn't have authority to it, which was a lie; Vietnam War; the war fractured the country and doesn't believe it has recovered yet; Kent State request; got involved w/ the incident in Dr. Haas office because asked to; he also had somewhat understanding w/ the students; also had a high opinion of her and she was alone in the office; Dr. Haas; she had little family (only recalls a niece); school became her family and was like a mother figure; knew everything that was going on; open door policy and always willing to talk w/ both faculty and students; open and direct person; knew a great deal; Position as president; many believe being the only woman among the four schools hurt her; she did change a bit over the years; Atmosphere of having woman president; most faculty respected to her; you will always have people who dislike administration because of their position as administrator; WestConn and Danbury area; school looked down upon by many in community; always viewed as the Normal School; community hasn't given support as much as would be desired; Normal School attitude starting to disappear now; never got attention for their activities and concerts in local press; has been work by school w/ community to give college more attention; Continuing Education; Priority of community; more concerned w/ football team than college itself; Soccer; played soccer from time he was a kid; when he got here, there was no soccer; worked w/ school and athletic department to start a team; coached for seven years until athletic department expanded; Coach Hines took over for him and he became a referee; few students had ever played game when program started; pleased w/ current program; game has changed, quality improved; not as interested in game as he once was; 1980s at WestConn; the distance in his age w/ students is much greater; most students in math don't stop in to talk; found most of the students who needed help, never asked for it; never got into politics of the time; few contact w/ students then; JFK assassination; Relationship w/ students; towards the end, got to know few; best relationships come from early years; Conflict between PhD. Professors and non; PhD. Professors; never personally had any conflict; tends to get along w/ everybody; math department was good (only one person had to be let go); internal friction in departments usually had nothing to do w/ PhD. Degree; having mixture was very good for the school; Reflection of career; satisfied w/ his career overall; no regrets about going into the profession (side B): Distance w/ students; expansion of school did have some effect; Honor's program; he had attempted to start program; went to various universities to see other programs; Memories of Dr. Haas; when he got interviewed, he was nervous and needed the job; went to her office and had 20 minute discussion; after discussion, he went to leave and wasn't sure what door to exit (there was three doors), which she laughed about; another time was when he went w/ students to celebrate in NY State (which had lower drinking age); next day she talked w/ him about it (she knew what happened); Skit Night and Sing Night; each class put on these skits and do original numbers; skits were generally quite funny; contest between the classes and tried to get judges from outside, but problem was skits were usually about college and judge may not understand the joke; one year, someone in freshman class wrote skit about a somber skit about Vietnam, which judges voted for; when similar thing happened next year, students stop being interested; Faculty growth; meetings to senate; Dr. Gertrude Braun, someone form history department, and himself got together to hammer out a constitution for the senate; he got elected president of the senate for first two years; His family; first wife died in an accident, later remarried; his second wife had three children as did he; her oldest son had done poorly in college first time around, but wanted to come back; he addressed the Senate that students should be given opportunity to get fresh start; has benefited many students since; Basic Studies; college enrollment had fallen and needed to be brought up to save faculty; purpose was to take high school grads not ready for college and prepare them for a regular college program; there are two ways of looking at it (one positive and other negative); question of how to teach these students came about as many professors had never dealt w/ students of this caliber; Faculty Association; pre; Union organization the college had; comprised of several committees; Unions; came in during 1970s (w/ AAUP coming out as union of choice); possible to become full; professor w/ having PhD.; Non; Western Cultures; WestConn was one of the few colleges in the country to require it; believes is was a "feather in the cap" of WestConn for that distinction; John Tufts; gave him a call one day believing a student had plagiarized his work; when he asked if it was a certain student, he told him it was his work; this student's sister is married to Dr. Alberetti
      - Elsie Ryan (interview) Creator: Ryan, Elsie Interviewer(s): Jim King and Dave Delvecchia Interview location: unknown Running time: 50 min., ca.Jun 13, 1905; 38914; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 11, Item 62)
        Topics discussed: (side A): Role at WestConn; was a secretary in several departments/areas; began as secretary in social science department; followed by being secretary for Dr. Cook until he retired; then worked for Dr. Teal who replaced Cook before he retired; worked for 2 executive deans, followed working in education department; Student activities; didn't know many until working in education department; placed students into student teaching jobs; Dr. Haas; had an open door policy; was always here early; she was down to Earth and a remarkable woman; library named after her; Library; opened in 1969; prior to that, it was located in Old Main; it was beautiful until they painted it; Dr. Bersi and Dr Feldman; not liked because lack of communication; no open door policy for either; Dorms; Fairfield Hall was the first dorm; guys weren't allowed in beginning; Basic Studies program; began in 1973; Vietnam; no problems on campus; no protesting; Name change; college to university; no one seemed to really notice; Dr. Bersi; close door policy, faculty felt kind of shut out; Dr Feldman; seems very standoffish; charming to talk to; Faculty; too many assistants and high paying jobs; high position people; some unnecessary jobs in the administration; Catherine Pickett; works same job as she did; Tensions at WestConn; confrontations between faculty and administration; poll on Feldman's competence a/ a lot of negative response; Unions at WestConn; she currently works for AAUP; first union began around 1976; helped w/ grievances the faculty had; some were more involved than others; Large enrollment at CSU schools; Saul Meeks; excellent teacher and good for the students; stepped on too many toes and went about things the wrong way; she had a confrontation w/ him over use of Xerox machine; he could be abrasive at times; started the credit union; most students liked him; now teaching at small school in Midwest; Westside campus; split campus; it was a hassle for both students and faculty; was talk about moving entirely to Westside, but now keeping midtown; money prevents it from happening; Racial problems; not aware of any race problems; small campus keeps any problems out; Well; balanced school; Sports; too much emphasis placed on sports; never cut budget to the sports; most minorities come to Western for sports programs; many athletes were in the Basic Studies program (side B): Student evaluation; teachers evaluating if students could make it as a teacher; one student in a wheelchair was told by one teacher he didn't think he would make it as a teacher; physical education was once a requirement to become a teacher; Western evolvement; the business school grew; named after Ancell, who donated money to Western; started by John Bratton; now education, business, and criminal justice are over on Westside; Bulletin boards; amount of advertisement; Stan Klein; worked w/ him for 5 years; was chairman of the education department; Faculty interest; faculty in education department care about students; Dr. Janick and Dr. Leopold are similar; Truman Warner; was her first boss when she began at Western; he was chairman of the social science/history department then; Enjoyed time at WestConn; made many friends over the years; miss them, but keep in touch w/ most of them
      - Lois Rycroft (interview) Creator: Rycroft, Lois Interviewer(s): Geoffrey A. Gallop Interview location: Job at school in Woodbury Running time: 43 min., May 13, 1992; 38913; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 11, Item 63)
        Topics discussed: (side A): Background; transferred into WestConn; had an associates degree, but had three children and needed more; felt at time teaching was a 180 days per year job (was proved wrong); was immediately hired in Woodbury after graduating WestConn; taught in kindergarten until she moved to teaching 3rd grade, later 4th; taught for 23 years; began when she was 34; she is taking early retirement; Future trends of teaching; believes in teaching positive connection w/ different groups; not sure if trend will be to make all schools diversified; believes problems don't come from schools, rather the family; Managing three children and school; Dr. Haas was very helpful in accommodating a schedule for her; had little time to read assignments; she had good grades, but wish she had better; found not being on campus was more beneficial; Non; trads vs. traditional students; non; trads tend to work harder than traditional students; never experienced any conflicts herself; traditional students complaining about non; trads being the "teacher's pet"; Campus activities; unable to participate in any activity; wanted to be in orchestra; her children were young at time; sometime brought her youngest w/ her (others did the same); Parking; not a problem for her; she always liked to be there ahead of time; Activities; supported plays; Sports; was very popular; football, baseball was there; Impressions of WestConn graduates; hard; working professionals; Curriculum; came from a liberal arts background; when she transferred here, only some were able to transfer; Classes; remembers a speech class she had; she had always been shy; her professor allowed her to feel comfortable; Education courses; the basic classes; Student teaching; different then, they were given two assignments; second assignment changed and she got hired w/ pay because of her work in her first assignment; she was able to put that towards retirement after she became certified; Dr. Haas; she was like everyone's mother; caring and gifted; devoted her life to the college; Campus layout/buildings; White Street was able to park on; was very impressed when she recently saw Westside campus; first impression was it was similar to her old high school; Old Main, Berkshire, Higgins, Fairfield all there; library was in Old Main; student lounge area was there; Social issues; more serious younger students than when she first went to college; capital punishment, euthanasia, and the same similar issues today; Commitments of older students; involved w/ activities for her children; church involvement; Commuting; I; 84 wasn't heavily congested then; had little problems getting to the college; Mothers and non; trads; always wished there had been a daycare service at the campus; schools try to accommodate everyone, but impossible to do so; numbers of non; trads has increased; Opinion of WestConn; many knew WestConn as being a great school; coming from Boston area to hear about WestConn was great; music education was also highly thought of; Highly respected teachers; Dr. Stephen Lovett (a former superintendent in Region 14; Woodbury); Dr. Charlotte Isham (left and came back to join faculty at Western); Closing comments; would like to see how many who finish at Western go into a field prepared for it
      - Clara Semsel (interview) Creator: Semsel, Clara Interviewer(s): Geramy Noone and Judy Malin Interview location: Semsel's home in Stamford, CT Running time: 35 min., Apr 15, 1992; 38912; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute (micro cassette)] (Box 11, Item 65)
        Coverage: 1928-1973
        Topics discussed: (side A): Danbury Normal School; began in 1928 and graduated in 1930; taught theory and method of teaching; First job; went to Washington, CT to teach; 3 out of the 5 girls from Stamford got jobs because of Depression; only stayed one year there because she got married; Class of 1930; classes divided into 3 divisions; maiden name was Pfeiffer and therefore in third division; May Sherwood; Fairfield Hall; was new when she got there and stayed there; went home on weekends (got rides from her boyfriend); Roads; still rural and not great; one girl from Greenwich actually walked to and from; Social activities; had several holiday parties at Fairfield Hall; Tunnel; Old Main; only building; Graduation; in the high school (now White Hall); wore cap and gowns; Student teaching; first experience done in Sherman, CT in one room school house; 2nd year she taught at Balmforth Ave School; Helen Donovan; 5th grade teacher at Balmforth; Entrance into Normal School; high school records; Traveling into town; had to be back to serve meals; usually walked down White Street; Weekends; most people went home on weekends; "County School"; most students came from the Fairfield County area; Trolley on White Street; Danbury State Teacher's College (1950s); psychology courses and art classes; degree program; classes in Stamford; Association w/ Southern CT College (New Haven); special education program was new; teachers were doctors from Yale; Degree; graduated from DSTC w/ bachelor of science; Job after degree; had high hopes and aspirations; worked w/ students w/ physical disabilities; previous teacher had a nervous breakdown (been student at Southern); Experience; previous work in special ed prepared her; Special ed program; conducted one; on; one teaching and home instruction; later groups were the preferred method; there had been no program prior to her coming in; Equipment; Classroom conduct; wore slacks and sat on the floor; Needs of students; did what she had to in order to meet the student needs; Substituted kindergarten thru 4th grade in the 1940s; Waterside and Hart Schools; Retired in 1973; got an addition 6 years and 9 months added to her retirement; had to retire on the advice of her doctor; Special education; socially unacceptable; memories of a student named "Kathy" who had cystic fibrosis; goal was to make these students feel equal to other students; travel time was 5 hours per day; it was an unusual program, but has now expanded; it is now socially accepted; Memories as student at Normal School; Fairfield Hall; wasn't noisy; had strict rules; house mothers enforced them, like making sure beds were made properly; Typical day at DNS; rigid w/ classes going on all day; study periods; Library; in Old Main; Sports/physical activities; learn games to play w/ students; but had no PE; Athletic fields; were located behind the school; Parking; no problems existed because no cars; Food; no complaints; not "institutional food"; home cooking; Scrapbook; kept one of her days at DNS w/ her papers
      - Dr. Violet Skorina (interview) Creator: Skorina, Dr. Violet Interviewer(s): Alice Hancock and Fran Zaccagnini Interview location: Skorina's home in Newtown, CT Running time: 90 min., Apr 22, 1991; 38911; Number of tapes:2 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 11, Item 67, 68)
        Coverage: 1960s-1991